hi welcome to the lamrim retreat the
steps of the path to liberation I'd like
to welcome Stanley Chen my translator
thank you for coming
and you know thank you for trying to say
over and over
so as you as you probably know this is
our 35th steps to the path retreat
and we are going through one of the
greatest books in my opinion ever
written in this world
it's called the gift of liberation put
in your hand and it's a beautiful idea
that if you study this book and if you
read this book
that it's like somebody just coming and
giving you freedom of liberation
at this time we're going to be doing
this retreat at home
because of the virus situation around
the world
and I think it might even be better
so each day we're gonna do about half an
hour
and it will go for 25 days and I I think
it'll be a great format for all of us
and we'll also be doing meditations
together during that time
so each segment each day is gonna have
its own name
and each segment will have its own ideas
behind it
and each segment has its own main image
or picture
so what you see here in the picture
our steps going into the sky and there's
a door in the sky
and that's the meaning of the word Lum
rim
I like to think of it like when you buy
a piece of furniture from Ikea
you get a paper and it says first do
this then do that then do that didn't do
that
and you don't have to think too much you
just do the first thing you know hook
these two things together
then okay what's the second thing just
screw the screw here
then you just you know it's for dummies
and you don't think about the chair
you're making
you just do those instructions one by
one
I don't know about you but I get scared
when I buy those furniture that I have
to put together
and I look at all the papers and all the
screws and I think oh I'm gonna fail
and in my long life what I learned
just shut up
open the box get the instruction book
don't look at the whole thing don't look
at all the parts
just look at the first sentence put this
groove in this hole
and then I do that and I feel okay then
I said okay I'm ready for the second one
and then just if I take it piece by
piece
step-by-step and I don't worry too much
really about what I'm gonna get at the
end
then suddenly the less Gruen in
and suddenly I have a beautiful chair
My partner Veronica so you're so smart
and actually I'm not smart I'm stupid I
just do one by one
Selam realm is the same
just do the steps dummy one by one
it's suddenly one day you look down you
don't have a chair
you have a Buddha party you're like oh
I'm done
so things like that
just take the steps one by one
enjoy it stab focus on Easter
and then by the end your Buddha and you
didn't have to do anything
okay so we started these retreats in
usually seven to ten days
and oftentimes we went to Diamond
mountain retreat center
and more recently to other other
countries
we have a very pleasant annual retreat
in the summer in Guadalajara Mexico
you
and nowadays we have a special retreat
in Bali each year at around December
and Jasmine Yao from Guangzhou and her
team
they have like 700 people come
to a beautiful hotel
and we enjoy swimming in the ocean
so we'll still be doing those retreats
if the virus has settled down by July
we'll see you in Mexico
is a very beautiful place
and then in December we'll see you in
Bali
in in October we'll do a special retreat
at Diamond Mountain in Arizona in
America
so each time we do a retreat
at the beginning I like to tell you how
far did we go how far do we have to go
and I can see from how fast we are going
and by the way I am NOT I am purposely
not going fast
they say when you drink an old wine I
don't drink a wine
but you should drink it slow
enjoy the taste you know swishing around
in your mouth
and then swallows so I want to study the
steps of the path like that
we are going slow
in English we say we are savoring the
taste we're enjoying the taste
and and we are stopping off many times
to go deeper and in some of these
sessions will just do a meditation the
whole time
and so my dream is that these teachings
on the steps to the palace
the total plan is going to take 23 years
we already finished 10 years
and my total plan is 13 more years
we if we go on schedule
we will finish in 2039
we'll be 87 years old
Stanley will be 20 I think
just kidding and so in my feeling in my
opinion
I want you to I want these teachers to
be part of your whole life
so 23 years is a big part of anybody's
adult life
and my dream is that you have this
support in your life
for 23 years and every year three or
four times
you'll have the opportunity to go to
another retreat if you want in person
but we also broadcast them for feet
if we might charge we might ask you to
help with the cost of the airplane if
you have to come there
or the hotel cost
or the cost of these cameras and all of
this equipment
but there's no charge for the teaching
and so for 23 years I want you to just
enjoy these classes
and I think it will be a foundation for
your life
my teacher took 30 years
he taught it twice in 30 years
and for me it gave me a foundation for
the happiness of my life
so okay it's the 35th retreat now
we'll finish this book after 50 retreats
then this book has a sisterhood
which is called the great steps on the
path by je tsongkhapa
actually that lamrim was written before
this love him
and when that steps to the path reached
the last two of the six perfections
which is meditation and emptiness then
takapa there's a story he had trouble
writing
and he started but he wasn't doing a
very good job
and then he prayed to manjushri the
angel of wisdom
and then it then he was able to finish
the section about meditation and
emptiness
and it's something like 200 pages
so for dessert
after we finished the 50 retreat
let's do another 40 retreats
about this great great presentation of
meditation how to meditate and how to
see emptiness
so that's our plan your life will go
through many changes
during this 33 years turtle
your life will go through many changes
sometimes you might be very interested
in this retreat
you will travel to Mexico or to Bali or
America to see those retreats
and then sometimes your family life or
your business life or your personal
emotions will change for a few years
and maybe you will just watch them on
the on the video
or maybe you will decide you too busy to
watch them
that our plan a sea ice plant
we will video everything
you'll have 33 years of videos
and when you're ready
anytime you want you can go on the ACA
website and you can see you can you can
access these videos
so don't don't worry too much about it
if you feel very interested
and flied to where the retreat is being
held
if you're busy then watch it online
if you're super busy save it for later
that our commitment
is that in your life
you will have these many years of
teachings
they will be ready for you anytime
you're ready
in my experience when people get a
serious illness like cancer
or something happens big in their life
like their their husband or wife passes
away
then they need support
and these videos on the steps the path
they will be waiting for you when you're
ready
they'll be here and we make that
commitment to you
all right so let's talk about the big
divisions or the big parts we've already
finished
in these last 10 years
the steps of the path are divided into
three big divisions
the short name is Cuba truth
everything
in Cuba Chambal give achoo means the
teachings for people of lowest capacity
and lowest capacity person in the lung
it's a somebody who's worried are they
gonna go down after they die
and right now maybe you're not worried
about it
but if something happens to you
if you get a serious disease there you
get into an accident of some kind
it will become the most important thing
in your life
like where am I going after this
and how can I get some insurance that I
won't go down
so that motivation or that capacity
it's called literally it's called a
small person
then a medium person and we finished it
and if you if you didn't hear those
early retreats you can find them online
and we'll put up all the links for you
the second big motor section is called
medium people medium motivation
and these people are like even if I'm
reborn even if I don't go down as an
animal
even if I'm born as a human
it's so much trouble
you know I would like to reach nirvana
and then I don't have to go back to a
life full of problems
getting older and older my body falling
apart
losing my family
okay I I don't I don't even want to go
through a human life again
I would like to find you can say a human
life but but one s we call our hot or
someone who reached nirvana
and they will never again live a life
with any trouble in it
and in the highest section of this
teaching
is a cable Chambal these are called
great people
and their motivation is more complete
say even if I get out of all ping
it wouldn't be very nice if my family
cannot come with me and my friends
cannot come with me
and in fact all the people in the world
and all the people in in the many-worlds
of this universe
I was reading an article in a science
magazine yesterday
and and they've located thousands of
planets thousands of stars that have
planets
and according to Buddha
there are people on some of those
planets
and they are also going through the same
trouble than we go through
so part of being a bodhisattva
you just don't you don't just think
about your own family
and you don't just think about your own
neighbors
you think about people all over the
world
if you study this teaching
you also realize your neighbors include
many other planets
and we have to take care of all of them
so that's a highest motivation
now we are in the middle of the media
motivation right now after ten years
and that had two big parts
one is called turbid energy look Kappa
which means to try to have the
motivation to reach a life which has no
pain
yeah how can I get in your mother which
is mayor
Tunku
and then the second big part of the
medium person's motivation
it's uh okay how do you what's the path
to get to know
and to study the path to get to Nirvana
you have to study something else
which is called conjunct or a Jew grim
Samba which means how did I get in this
mess in the first place
you
and that question how did I get in this
mess in the first place
it has three paths
first part how did I start to have
negative thoughts like anger or desire
or jealousy
then secondly when I have those negative
thoughts how do I collect karma
then because of that karma
I'm gonna go through death
and I will have to cross to another life
and then we explore what does it feel
like to die what does it feel like to go
to the next life
and we're in the middle of that section
so that's the end of the first segment
the first segment was called where have
the steps taken us
and we came a long way in ten years
and now we are going to discuss you know
how is it that we die what happens to us
after we die how do we go to the next
so we'll see you next time in segment
two
thank you
you